Finding Aid for the Richmond Croom Beatty Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
The Richmond Croom Beatty Papers
undated
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0038
3.36 linear feet
BIOGRAPHICAL SKETCH
Richmond Croom Beatty was born January 6, 1905, a son of William Henry and Caroline Barbour Beatty. He received his early education in Barker Elementary School and Central High School in Birmingham. He received his A.B. degree from Birmingham Southern University in 1924, his M.A. degree from Vanderbilt in 1928, and his Ph.D. degree from Vanderbilt in 1930.
Behind the incisive, irascible wit of Richmond Croom Beatty, Professor of English and faculty member since 1937, seethes the man’s scorn of sycophancy, sham and the second-rate. And lightly covered by the casual air lies an unrelenting demand for firstclass work, on his students’ part and his own. This even-voiced, sharp-shooting Alabamian - born in Shawnee, Okla. before his father, a cotton buyer, took his family back to Birmingham - is one of the men who kept Vanderbilt’s English department high on the national list. His own reputation in letters is formidable; he is the author of four biographies - William Byrd, Bayard Taylor, Macaulay and Lowell - and the editor of seven significant literary volumes. Of equal weight in the academic scales is his work with graduate scholars; he directs a vast number of M.A. and Ph.D. theses, often as many as a dozen at a time. But his talents are not limited to the department. His articles in recent years added flavor and fire to the Alumnus; one of them, a reply to a Collier’s attack on fraternities, was reprinted by the “Greeks” as their own apologia. He was a fraternity man himself - as well as hurdles runner, pole vaulter and track captain - at Birmingham Southern and at Vanderbilt. (He helped defray his tuition by doing chemical analysis for a cast iron pipe firm and, later, with a job “on the rim” for the Birmingham Age-Herald). He began teaching at Memphis State and, five years later, in 1935, became a faculty member at the University of Alabama. During his twenty-one years of study and teaching at Vanderbilt he has never been or tried to be “all things to all men”; rather he bas made his name mean merely a pair of virtues not always, in other men, found together: talent and integrity.
“Vanderbilt Portraits No. 36: [Richmond Croom Beatty]. Vanderbilt Alumnus Magazine, May-June 1954 (vol. 39 no. 5): 5.
Scope and Content Note
The Richmond Croom Beatty Papers (1905-1961) include correspondence and writings by Beatty as well as reviews, newspaper clippings, photographs, journal and magazine articles, class notes, index cards and manuscripts of writings by others. The Papers consist of nine Hollinger boxes (3.55 linear feet).
The bulk of the materials cover the 1930s through 1950.
Beatty’s writings are divided into several series: book manuscripts, poetry, book reviews, journal articles, general notes on literature and class notes. There is also a box of handwritten notes on index cards.
- CORRESPONDENCE-OUTGOING-INCOMING-POEMS
  - Correspondence (Outgoing) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence (Incoming, A-B) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence (Incoming, C) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence (Incoming, Donald Davidson) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence (Incoming, E-G) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence (Incoming, H-J) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence (Incoming, W.S. Knickerbocker) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence (Incoming, L) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence (Incoming, M-N) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence (Incoming, George Marion O’Donnell) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence (Incoming, O-Q) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence (Incoming, R) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence (Incoming, S) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence (Incoming, Allen Tate) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence (Incoming, W) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence (Incoming, incomplete signatures) (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Poems by Richmond C. Beatty, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Poems by Richmond C. Beatty, 1935-1936 (1) (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Poems by Richmond C. Beatty, 1935-1936 (2) (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Poems by Richmond C. Beatty, 1935-1936 (3) (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Poems by Richmond C. Beatty, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Poems by Richmond C. Beatty, 1941-1942; 1945; 1948 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Poems by Richmond C. Beatty, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Poems by Richmond C. Beatty, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Poems by Richmond C. Beatty, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Poems by Richmond C. Beatty, undated fragments (Box 1, Folder 26)
- WRITINGS
  - Manuscript of James Russell Lowell (1) [Preface, Chapters I-VI] (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Manuscript of James Russell Lowell (2) [Chapters VII-XIII] (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Manuscript of James Russell Lowell (3) [Chapters XIV-XX] (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Manuscript of James Russell Lowell (4) [Chapters XXI-XXIV] (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Manuscript of Lord Macaulay: Victorian Liberal (1) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Manuscript of Lord Macaulay: Victorian Liberal (2) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Manuscript of Lord Macaulay: Victorian Liberal (3) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Manuscript of Lord Macaulay: Victorian Liberal (4) (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Manuscript of Lord Macaulay: Victorian Liberal (5) (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Manuscript of Lord Macaulay: Victorian Liberal (6) (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Manuscript fragment, proposal and notes for Lord Macaulay: Victorian Liberal (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Lord Macaulay: Victorian Liberal excerpts; Trevelyan’s notes (Box 2, Folder 12)
- WRITINGS
  - Manuscript of Biographies of American Authors (1) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Manuscript of Biographies of American Authors (2) (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Manuscript of Biographies of American Authors (3) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Manuscript of Biographies of American Authors (4) (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Manuscript of Biographies of American Authors (5) (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Manuscript of The Southern Renaissance (1918-1950), Chapter I, “The Renaissance Per Se” (pages l-25) (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Manuscript of The Southern Renaissance (1918-1950), Chapter II, “Recent Southern Political Figures” (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Manuscript of The Southern Renaissance (1918-1950), Chapter III, “Recent Southern Magazines ...” (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Manuscript of The Southern Renaissance (1918-1950), Chapter IV, “The Revisionist School of Southern Historians” (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Manuscript of The Southern Renaissance (1918-1950), Chapter V, “Literary Criticism” (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Manuscript of The Southern Renaissance (1918-1950), Chapter VI-C, “Robert Penn Warren” (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Manuscript of The Southern Renaissance (1918-1950), Chapter VI-B, “The Ordeal of Thomas Wolfe” (pages 209-232) (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Manuscript of The Nashville Group (1) John Crowe Ransom (pages 26-53) (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Manuscript of The Nashville Group (2) Allen Tate (pages 54-75) (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Manuscript of The Nashville Group (3) Donald Davidson (pages 76-97) (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Manuscript of The Nashville Group (4) Robert Penn Warren (pages 98-121) (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Manuscript of The Woman’s Vision (Ellen Glasgow, Elizabeth M. Roberts, Caroline Gordon) (pages 122-154] (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Manuscript of “Eudora Welty and Katherine Ann Porter” (pages 155-169) (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Manuscript of Four Poets (Jarrell, Bishop, Stuart, Moore) [pages 244-272] (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Manuscript of “Hugh Henry Brackenridge on Frontier Democracy” (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Manuscript of “Irving as Humorist” (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Manuscript fragment (American Poetry: Pound, Eliot, Tate, Crane) (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Manuscripts of book reviews by Beatty (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Manuscript of A Biographical History of English Literature (1) (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Manuscript of A Biographical History of English Literature (2) (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Manuscript of A Biographical History of English Literature (3) (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Manuscript of “A Reaction to Keats” (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Manuscript of “Macaulay and Carlyle” (Box 3, Folder 28)
- NOTES - WRITINGS
  - Notes: American Literature (General) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Notes: Emerson (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Notes: Thoreau, etc. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Notes: Southern Literature, etc. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Notes: Fugitives, etc. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Grade book, lecture notebook, etc. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Notes: English and Continental Literature (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous manuscripts and notes (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Manuscript of “A Note on Proletarian Aesthetic” (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Manuscript of “College Presidents (A Note on Apostasy)” (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Biographical and autobiographical material (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Reviews of Beatty’s books, etc. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - English 302; 304: Ph.D. examinations (University of Chicago) (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Notes and syllabi: English 535 (American Literature) (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Vanderbilt University theses in English through, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- PHOTOGRAPHS - NEWSPAPER CLIPPINGS - MISCELLANEOUS
  - Table of Contents, etc. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Photographs and sketches (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Manuscripts by others (1) (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous manuscripts by others (2) (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Agrarian documents (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Poems by others (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Primary stories (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Lowell correspondence (1) (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Lowell correspondence (2) (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Lowell correspondence (3) (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Newspaper clippings of book reviews by Beatty, (1930s) (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Newspaper clippings of book reviews by Beatty, (1940s) (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Newspaper clippings of book reviews by Beatty, (1950s) (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Newspaper clippings of reviews of William Bvrd, (1932) (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Newspaper clippings of reviews of Bayard Taylor, (1937) (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Newspaper clippings of reviews of Lord Macaulay, (1939) (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Newspaper clippings of reviews of James R. Lowell, (1942) (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Newspaper clippings of reviews of books edited by Beatty, (1940-1945) (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Newspaper clippings of items about Beatty (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Newspaper clippings of items about Beatty family (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Newspaper clippings referring to Davidson, Cheney, and Warren (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Newspaper clippings referring to friends of Beatty (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Newspaper clippings of miscellaneous book reviews (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Miscellaneous newspaper clippings (Box 5, Folder 25)
- JOURNAL AND MAGAZINE ARTICLES
  - “Seminal Emissions” (pamphlet) by James C. Jackson, M.D. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Reviews in brief of Beatty’s Lord Macaulay (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous manuscript notes (three sheets) (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - “Digging Up Daylight” from The American Review (pamphlet) (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Handwritten memo dated, March 30, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - The Saturday Review of Literature, (December 26, 1936) (two copies) (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Newsweek, (January 23, 1939) (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - The Nation, (February 11, 1939) (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - The Saturday Review of Literature, (June 24, 1950) (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - The New Republic, (March 8, 1939) (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - River: A Magazine in the Deep South, (June 1937) (two copies) (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - The Observer: A Literary publication, (October - November, 1933) (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - The Hopkins Review, (Summer 1951) (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - “The Ninth Part of Speech (A Verse Letter: To Louis Zahner) by Donald Davidson [inscribed by Davidson] (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - These Fragments (pamphlet) by George Marion O’Donnell [Reprint from the April Number of The Sewanee Review, 1935] (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Rains (Piuies) St.-John Pearse, (1945) (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - The Fugitive: Clippings and Comment Collected by Merrill Moore (literary magazine) (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - “The Ocular History of James Joyce” by Noah D. Fabricant, M.D. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - “William Byrd and the Virginian Author of The Wanderer” by Kenneth Ballard Murdock [Reprinted from Harvard Studies and Notes in Philology and Literature, Volume 17 (1935)] (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - “A Great Teacher’s Legacy” (Tribute to Edwin Mims) [one sheet] (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - “Poe and the Southern Literary Tradition” by Jay B. Hubbell [Reprint from the University of Texas Studies in Literature and Language, Volume II, Number 2, Summer 1960] (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - The Saturday Review of Literature, (January 23, 1943) (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - The English Journal, (April, 1954) (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - “The New South and the Conservative Tradition” by Donald Davidson (pamphlet) [inscribed by Davidson] (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - “Waltzing Matilda” by William Power (graduate student in English at Vanderbilt) (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - “Structural Devices in the Works of Faulkner” by Harry Campbell [inscribed by author] (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Governor Robett L. Taylor and the Blair Educational Bill in Tennessee by Daniel M. Robison, (1932) (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - The Political Background of Tennessee’s War of the Roses by Daniel M. Robison (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Tennessee Politics and the Agrarian Revolt (1886-1896) by Daniel M. Robison, (1933) (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Vanderbilt Alumnus, (December 1939) (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Fundamentals of Air Fighting (pamphlet) (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - VU 75 (brochure of Vanderbilt history in brief) (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Review of James Russell Lowell (1942) by Roy F. Nichols of University of Pennsylvania (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Review of Wright and Tinling’s The Secret Diary of William Byrd of Westover, 1709-1712 by Beatty (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - The Southwestern Journal, (December 1934) (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - “Brief Articles and Notes” (pamphlet of varied literary commentaries) [two copies] (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - The South Atlantic Quarterly, (April, 1948) (Box 6, Folder 7)
- INDEX CARDS
  - Miscellaneous handwritten notes on index cards (Box 7, Folder no folders)
- CORRESPONDENCE- WRITINGS
  - Correspondence (Outgoing), July 5, 1943-November 8, 1943 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence (Outgoing), November 9, 1943-January 11, 1944 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence (Outgoing), January 13, 1944 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence (Outgoing), Undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence (Incoming) B - Davidson, W.W. (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence (Incoming) Davidson, Donald - Leatherman (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence (Incoming) McCarthy - Ransom (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence (Incoming) Rose - Stuart (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence (Incoming) Sullivan - Tate (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence (Incoming) Taylor-Williams (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence (Incoming) Woods-Unidentified (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Manuscript: Dedication, Preface, Title Page, Table of Contents (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Manuscript: Notes on the Authors (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Manuscript: “Writing at Vanderbilt” by Beatty (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Manuscript: Introduction (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Manuscript: Introduction (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Manuscripts of entries: Boone and Brooks (Prose) (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Manuscripts of entries: Cheney and Davidson (Prose) (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Manuscripts of entries: Haun and Lytle (Prose) (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Manuscripts of entries: Nixon and Owsley (Prose) (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Manuscripts of entries: Parks (Prose) (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Manuscripts of entries: Ransom (Prose) (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Manuscripts of entries: Still - Stuart (Prose) (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Manuscripts of entries: Tate - Wade (Prose) (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Manuscripts of entries: Warren - Woods (Prose) (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Manuscripts of entries: Clark - Moore (Poetry) (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Manuscripts of entries: Moses - Parks (Poetry) (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Manuscripts of entries: Ransom - Tate (Poetry) (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Manuscripts of entries: Warren - Wills (Poetry) (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Miscellaneous manuscripts (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - Newspaper clipping: review of Giles J. Patterson’s Journal of a Southern Student (1846-1848) which is edited and introduced by Beatty; from The Nashville Banner, (January 24, 1945) (Box 8, Folder 31)
- WRITINGS
  - Typescript of James Russell Lowell (Box 9, Folder no folders)